<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Corps of Engineers, St. Louis District</origin>
<pubdate>20161230</pubdate>
<title>03645188</title>
<geoform>remote-sensing image</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>US Army Corps of Engineers St. Louis District</pubplace>
<publish>US Army Corps of Engineers St. Louis District</publish>
</pubinfo>
<onlink>http://www.mvs.usace.army.mil/index.html</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>
Fugro Geospatial Inc acquired LiDAR with Leica sensor
ALS60 MPiA for the North Dakota LiDAR program. This portion
of the LiDAR program covers areas in North Dakota and South
Dakota which approximately totalled 9582 sq miles.
Acquisition occured Spring 2015.
The ALS60 sensor settings included acquisition at 7,000&apos;
AMT, 150 knots, 15% sidelap, pulse rate 109,600Hz, scan rate
50Hz, 34 degree field of view, 4,281ft swath width, maximum
along track spacing (occurs at FOV edge) of 2.37m in overlap
areas, maximum cross track spacing (occurs at Nadir) 1.17
meter, 3sigma post spacing of 1.34m, and a 3sigma point
density of 0.717points per square meter.  Each sensor was
also equipped with IPAS inertial measuring unit (IMU) and a
dual frequency airborne GPS receiver.  These settings
were used to meet or exceed 15cm vertical RMSE in flat
areas with minimial vegitation.
Final deliverables for the LiDAR are in UTM zone 14
coordinate system NAD83(2007) NAVD88 Geod03 meters
tiled 2,000m x 2,000m with an XY naming convention.
*******DELIVERABLES*****
***  1m_Int_IMG - 1-Meter Intensity image created
from all Lidar classes in *.img format
***  DEM_IMG - 1-Meter DEM created from .LAS ground
class and ARC 3D-Waterbodies
***  Metadata -  Flight logs and acquisition dates
***  Final_LAS - Classes included 1-Unclassified, 2-Ground,
3-Low Vegetation, 4-Med Vegetation, 5-High Vegetation,
6-Building, 7-Noise, 10-Ignored-Ground within 1m of water
edge, 11-Scan edge, 15-Water/Vegetation (This class was
used within areas of water/swampy waters/cat-tail
vegetation)
*** Shapefiles - Supplemental data including waterbodies
***  Survey Data RS
ACQUISITION DATES
LiDAR Block A -  11-15-2015 to 11-20-2015
LiDAR Block B -  03-26-2016 to 04-29-2016
LiDAR Block D -  03-28-2015 to 11-22-2015
</abstract>
<purpose>
USACE ST Louis District strives to develop partnerships
to leverage the planned acquisition of LiDAR and
imagery to better meet state, local, and federal needs and
generate a freely accessible seamless high-resolution
digital elevation model.  One of the products of this effort is
1.4m average post spacing LiDAR and its derivatives.
</purpose>
<supplinf>
USACE ST Louis District MISSION AND
OBJECTIVES
To provide a forum for collaborative research and
communication relative to flood damage reduction and
natural resource protection via basin universities, private
industry, government agencies, and non-government
organizations.
Utilize technical and professional expertise to help resolve
critical water management issues.
Facilitate enhanced networking of research professionals
from higher education institutions and federal, state, and
local agency personnel, environmental groups, and citizens
of the James Watershed to cooperate in solving the critical
water management and natural resource issues in the
basin.
Provide opportunities for faculty and students to receive
education, perform research, and gain experience on
subjects important to the region.  Prepare student for future
employment while providing valuable basic and applied
research.
</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>20160429</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>Ground Conditions</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>Irregular</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<bounding>
<westbc>-100.783892</westbc>
<eastbc>-100.757084</eastbc>
<northbc>+46.850044</northbc>
<southbc>+46.831649</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>None</themekt>
<themekey>LiDAR Acquisition</themekey>
<themekey>LiDAR</themekey>
<themekey>LiDAR 1.4m</themekey>
<themekey>USACE St Louis District</themekey>
<themekey>James River Watershed</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
<placekey>SD</placekey>
<placekey>South Dakota</placekey>
<placekey>ND</placekey>
<placekey>North Dakota</placekey>
<placekey>James River</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<accconst>There are no limitations for access.</accconst>
<useconst>
None other than the USACE ST Louis District and
supporting partners ask to be credited in any derived
products or services.
</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USACE ST Louis District</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
St. Louis District Public Affairs Office
1222 Spruce Street
</address>
<city>St. Louis</city>
<state>MO</state>
<postal>63103-2833</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(314) 331-8068</cntvoice>
<hours>8am to 5pm Central Time</hours>
<cntinst>http://www.mvs.usace.army.mil/</cntinst>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
<browse>
<browsen>None</browsen>
<browsed>None</browsed>
<browset>None</browset>
</browse>
</idinfo>
<dataqual>
<attracc>
<attraccr>
GPS phase data was post processed with continuous
kinematic survey techniques using &quot;On the Fly&quot; (OTF)
integer ambiguity resolution.  The GPS data was processed
with forward and reverse processing algorithms.  The
results from each process, using the data collected at the
airport and in project area, were combined to yield a single
fixed integer phase differential solution of the aircraft
trajectory.  The differences between the forward to reverse
solution within the project area were within project
specifications, indicating a valid and accurate
solution. An IMU was used to record precise changes in
position and orientation of the LIDAR scanner at a rate of
200 Hz.  All IMU data was processed post flight with a filter
to integrate inertial measurements and precise phase
differential GPS positions.  The resulting solution contains
geodetic position, omega, phi, kappa, and time for
subsequent merging with the laser ranging information.
</attraccr>
</attracc>
<logic>Tiling is based on the UTM14 coordinates.</logic>
<complete>Complete</complete>
<posacc>
<horizpa>
<horizpar>
Meets or exceeds horizontal accuracy of 0.6m RMSE
1.04 m at the 95% confidence level.
</horizpar>
</horizpa>
<vertacc>
<vertaccr>
Vertical elevations will meet or exceed 15.0 cm RMSE
0.30m at the 95% confidence level for bare
earth products.
</vertaccr>
</vertacc>
</posacc>
<lineage>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>USACE ST Louis District</origin>
<pubdate>20160315</pubdate>
<pubtime>Unknown</pubtime>
<title>http://www.mvs.usace.army.mil/</title>
<geoform>remote-sensing image</geoform>
<onlink>http://www.mvs.usace.army.mil/</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<typesrc>Digital copy</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>20150317</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>Acquisition Date</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>Georectifed LiDAR data sets</srccitea>
<srccontr>Digital Georectifed LiDAR.</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<procstep>
<procdesc>
AeroScan LiDAR timed reflection data and the IMU SOL
flies were processed together using LiDAR processing
software.  The data set for each flight line was checked for
project area coverage, data gaps between overlapping
flight lines, and tension/compression areas (areas where
data points are more or less dense than the average project
specified post spacing).  Using an iterative process that
involves analyzing raster difference calculations the
omega, phi, kappa angle corrections for the LiDAR
instrument were determined.  Corrections were applied to
the LiDAR data set. Extensive comparisons were made of
vertical and horizontal positional differences between
points common to two or more LiDAR flight lines.  An
intensity raster for each flight line was generated and
verified that intensity was recorded for each LiDAR point.
LiDAR ground points were compared to independently
surveyed and positioned ground control points at both the
airport bore-sight area and the project area. Based on the
results of these comparisons, the LiDAR data was vertically
biased to the ground.
(1) PRE-PROCESSING STAGE
LiDAR, GPS and IMU data are processed together using
LiDAR processing software.
The LiDAR data set for each flight line is checked for
project area coverage and LiDAR post spacing is checked
to ensure it meets project specifications.
The LiDAR collected at the calibration area is used to
correct the rotational, atmospheric, and vertical elevation
differences that are inherent to LiDAR data.
Intensity raster is generated to verify that intensity was
recorded for each LiDAR point.
LiDAR data is transformed to the specified project
coordinate system.
By utilizing the ground survey data collected at the
calibration site and project area, the LiDAR data is
vertically biased to the ground.
Comparisons between the biased LiDAR data and ground
survey data within the project area are evaluated and a
final RMSE value is generated to ensure the data meets
project specifications.
LiDAR data in overlap areas of project flight lines is
removed and data from all swaths is merged into a single
data set.
The data set is trimmed to the digital project boundary
including an additional buffer zone, which is typically about
50 meters (buffer zone assures adequate contour
generation
from the DEM).
The resulting data set is referred to as the raw LiDAR data.
(2) SURFACING STAGE
The raw LIDAR data is processed through a minimum
block mean algorithm and points are classified as either
bare earth or non-bare earth.
User developed &quot;macros&quot; that factor mean terrain angle
and height from the ground are used to determine bare
earth point classification.
The next phase of the surfacing process is a 2D edit
procedure that ensures the accuracy of the automated
feature classification.
Editors use a combination of imagery, intensity of the
LiDAR reflection and tin-editing software to assess points.
If required, the LiDAR data is filtered as necessary, using a
quadric error metric to remove redundant points to
generate a keypoint class. This method
leaves points where there is a change in the slope of
surfaces (road ditches) and eliminates points from evenly
sloped terrain (flat field) where the points do not affect the
surface.  When other classifications and derived products
are required, various applications and proprietary algorithms
are used to meet each customer&apos;s unique requirements.
</procdesc>
<procdate>20161230</procdate>
</procstep>
</lineage>
</dataqual>
<spref>
<horizsys>
<planar>
<gridsys>
<gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
<utm>
<utmzone>14</utmzone>
<transmer>
<sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer>
<longcm>-099.000000</longcm>
<latprjo>0.0</latprjo>
<feast>500000</feast>
<fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
</transmer>
</utm>
</gridsys>
<planci>
<plance>row and column</plance>
<coordrep>
<absres>.001</absres>
<ordres>.001</ordres>
</coordrep>
<plandu>Meters</plandu>
</planci>
</planar>
<geodetic>
<horizdn>North American Datum NAD83 (NSRS2007)</horizdn>
<ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80 (GRS 80)</ellips>
<semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis>
<denflat>298.257222101</denflat>
</geodetic>
</horizsys>
<vertdef>
<altsys>
<altdatum>North American Vertical datum of 1988 Geoid03</altdatum>
<altres>.001</altres>
<altunits>Meters</altunits>
<altenc>Implicit coordinate</altenc>
</altsys>
<depthsys>
<depthdn>No correction</depthdn>
<depthres>.001</depthres>
<depthdu>Meters</depthdu>
<depthem>Implicit coordinate</depthem>
</depthsys>
</vertdef>
</spref>
<eainfo>
<overview>
<eaover>
1.4m LiDAR Acquisition and Processing for USACE and
supporting partners.
</eaover>
<eadetcit>None</eadetcit>
</overview>
</eainfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USACE ST Louis District</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
St. Louis District Public Affairs Office
1222 Spruce Street
</address>
<city>St. Louis</city>
<state>MO</state>
<postal>63103-2833</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(314) 331-8068</cntvoice>
<hours>8am to 5pm Central Time</hours>
<cntinst>http://www.mvs.usace.army.mil/</cntinst>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<distliab>
In no event shall the creators, custodians, or distributors of
this information be liable for any damages arising out of its
use (or the inability to use it).
</distliab>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20161230</metd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USACE ST Louis District</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
St. Louis District Public Affairs Office
1222 Spruce Street
</address>
<city>St. Louis</city>
<state>MO</state>
<postal>63103-2833</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(314) 331-8068</cntvoice>
<hours>8am to 5pm Central Time</hours>
<cntinst>http://www.mvs.usace.army.mil/</cntinst>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
</metainfo>
</metadata>
